<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>motion streaks | Richard Schweitzer</title>
    <link>https://richardschweitzer.github.io/tag/motion-streaks/</link>
      <atom:link href="https://richardschweitzer.github.io/tag/motion-streaks/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>motion streaks</description>
    <generator>Wowchemy (https://wowchemy.com)</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Wed, 02 Feb 2022 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>https://richardschweitzer.github.io/media/icon_hu0b7a4cb9992c9ac0e91bd28ffd38dd00_9727_512x512_fill_lanczos_center_3.png</url>
      <title>motion streaks</title>
      <link>https://richardschweitzer.github.io/tag/motion-streaks/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>Coupling perception to action through incidental sensory consequences of motor behaviour</title>
      <link>https://richardschweitzer.github.io/publication/rolfsschweitzer2022/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 02 Feb 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://richardschweitzer.github.io/publication/rolfsschweitzer2022/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;This perspective paper is dedicated to the question how an active perceptual system deals with the sensory consequences of its own actions. For instance, in the field of active vision little is known about the consequences of large-field smear induced by the rapid image shift caused by saccades. Whereas such information is thought to hinder visual processing, new evidence is discussed that sheds light on the intriguing possibility of action-perception couplings, that is, the idea that perception is shaped by sensory consequences of actions.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Intrasaccadic motion streaks jump-start gaze correction</title>
      <link>https://richardschweitzer.github.io/publication/schweitzerrolfs2021_sciadv/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 23 Jul 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://richardschweitzer.github.io/publication/schweitzerrolfs2021_sciadv/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;In this piece we showed that the visual traces that moving objects induce during saccades can facilitate secondary saccades in both accuracy and saccade initiation latency. Secondary saccades are typically prompted when one saccade does not entirely reach a target or when the saccade target is displaced in mid-flight. Our results provide evidence against the widely acknowledged notion that our brains preemptively discard visual information which reaches the eye during saccades. The paper has received some peer and media attention, such as a well-written &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.science.org/doi/10.1126/sciadv.abk0043&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;commentary by Jasper Fabius and Stefan van der Stigchel&lt;/a&gt;, as well as articles in &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.nature.com/articles/d41586-021-02058-9&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Nature Research Highlights&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.aaas.org/news/human-eyes-absorb-visual-information-even-during-rapid-eye-movements&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;AAAS&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.newscientist.com/article/2285131-we-thought-our-eyes-turned-off-when-moving-quickly-but-thats-wrong/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;New Scientist&lt;/a&gt;, or &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.vozpopuli.com/next/ojos-movimientos-sacadicos.html&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Vozpópuli&lt;/a&gt; (see &lt;a href=&#34;https://rolfslab.org/2021/08/09/press-coverage-on-science-advances-paper/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;the Rolfslab&#39;s blog post&lt;/a&gt; for the full list). Notably, this study is the first one to apply the new TrackPixx eye tracking system, for which I have written a &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/richardschweitzer/TrackPixxToolbox&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Matlab toolbox&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Perceptual and Motor Consequences of Intra-saccadic Perception</title>
      <link>https://richardschweitzer.github.io/publication/schweitzer2020_dissertation/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 14 Dec 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://richardschweitzer.github.io/publication/schweitzer2020_dissertation/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Intra-saccadic motion streaks as cues to linking object locations across saccades</title>
      <link>https://richardschweitzer.github.io/publication/schweitzerrolfs2020_jov/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 01 Jul 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://richardschweitzer.github.io/publication/schweitzerrolfs2020_jov/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Whenever we make a saccade to an object, that object will travel from the periphery to the fovea at extremely high velocities. Depending on the visual features of the object, such motion can induce streaks, that may serve as visual clues to solve the problem of trans-saccadic object correspondence. Using a high-speed projection system operating at 1440 fps, we investigated to what extent human observers are capable of matching pre- and post-saccadic object locations when their only cue was an intra-saccadic motion streak, and compared their performance during saccades to a replay of the retinal stimulus trajectory presented during fixation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A toolbox for parsing Eyelink EDF files was implemented in R to analyze this series of experiments, which can be found &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/richardschweitzer/EyelinkEDFTools_R&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
